William J. Regan Papers
Wallingford Historic Preservation Trust
William J. Regan Papers
William J. Regan
2017.7.0001 - 2017.7.0135
5 linear ft. 2 file cabinet drawers plus 1 linear ft. of books
Wallingford Historic Preservation Trust
This collection consists of Mr. Regan's files from his time working in various management positions for Wallace Silver Company and and as a consultant for Kirk-Stieff.
Restrictions
Collection open for research by appointment only.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by the Regan family to Wallingford Historic Preservation Trust after Mr. Regan died in 2004. The material was packed in cardboard boxes in random order.
Biography
William Regan's first position, directly after graduation from Yale University, was at the Wallace Company in Wallingford. Wallace was a large silver manufacturing firm. Its products were Sterling Flatware, Sterling Holloware, Plated Holloware, and Dinnerware.
He began in 1930 as Assistant Dept. Head in the Sterling Division where he instituted an inventory control system and began assuming greater responsibilities in all fields of this division.
In 1939, he was promoted to General Superintendent of the Sterling Flatware, Sterling Holloware and Hotel Holloware lines, with duties including costs, quality, inventory and production.
The onset of WWII changed the focus of many US companies and Wallace was no exception. From 1941 to 1945, ninety percent of total company sales were in war products, and William had complete control of this project. At the same time, he set up and controlled the production of some sterling flatware designs in a plant in Indiana.
From 1945 through 1950, William was General Sales Manager of the Retail Division which included Sterling Flatware, Sterling Holloware, Plated Holloware and Trophies. These products were distributed through 4,000 carefully selected jewelry and department stores. The sales during this time increased from $2,066,000 in 1945 to $9,328,000 in 1950.
During the next fifteen years, in addition to his managerial position, William was also the company representative on the Sales Managers' Committee of the Sterling Silversmiths Guild which was an Industry Organization. William was also Assistant to the Vice President of Marketing from 1958 to 1960. This placed him in charge of merchandising, new product additions. and designing for Stainless Steel Flatware. At the same time, he was Manager of Dealer Relations for both Wholesale and Retail Divisions.
In 1953, a new division called Market & Sales Research was created and became a part of William's responsibilities. He flourished in this position, developing and supervising sales forecasts and sales expense budgets for the entire company.
Then in 1960, due to a sales re-organization, a result of a merger with Hamilton Watch Company, William became Assistant Director of the Sales-Retail Division. He transferred to Lancaster PA when the Wallace Company Headquarters moved there. He remained there for ten year as Director of Merchandising and then Director of Product Planning and Development. Prior to his retirement, sales in the year 1972 had increased to $17,600,000.
After his 1973 retirement, William worked for ten years as a consultant and Director of Product Development for Kirk Stieff in Baltimore, MD.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection consists of Mr. Regan's files from his time working for both Wallace Silver and consulting for Kirk-Stieff. This includes items such as stockholder correspondence, silver market prices, marketing programs and sterling, holloware and flatware sales promotions, catalogs, "Outline and history of Silver, Design, and Manufacturing Principles and Practice," "The Story of Silver," and "The Family Tree of the American Silverware Industry (1815-1965)," pictures and photographs 1950-1975, Talks on Silver given by William Regan, agendas and minutes of Sales meeting and conferences in the 1970s, quarterly and annual reports and numerous other documents. There is also a collection of Mr. Regan's books on silver.
Arrangement
All files are arranged in alphabetical order. An item by item inventory of the collection can be found in the collection files in the office archives.
Related Collections
There is also a Wallace Silver Company Collection donated directly from the Wallace company.
Separated Material
There are also 22 books on silver which were part of the donated Regan collection. These are located in the library portion of the archives.
- Inventory
  - A. B. Gense (Sweden), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0001)
  - American Metal Market - International Silver Report, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0002)
  - American Silver Museum, 1986-1996 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0003)
  - American Silver Museum Folders and Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0004)
  - Arthur Price of England, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0005)
  - Atlantic City, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0006)
  - Biography and Resume of William J. Regan, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0007)
  - Booklets - The Silver Market, 1954-1958 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0008)
  - Booklets - The Silver Market, 1962-1965 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0009)
  - Booklets - The Silver Market(The Silver Mkt 1987 and 1988 in Magazines- Reference), 1966-1969 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0010)
  - Cohr (Denmark), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0011)
  - Consumer Survey of Sterling Silver Holloware, 1974 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0012)
  - European Trip, 1973 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0013)
  - Family Tree of the American Silverware Industry:, 1815-1965 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0014)
  - Georg Jensen Silver - Price List, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0015)
  - Golf Magazine - Al Konetzni, Cartoonist, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0016)
  - Guild Information (Sterling Silversmiths Guild), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0017)
  - Guild Outings, 1967-1973 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0018)
  - Hamilton Watch Company's Annual Reports, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0019)
  - History of Silver (various articles), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0020)
  - HJORDIS HAUGAARD, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0021)
  - HMW Industries, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0022)
  - HMW Industries - Annual Reports, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0023)
  - International Silver Co, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0024)
  - International Silver Annual Reports 1966 (2), 1969 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0025)
  - Jewelers Almanac, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0026)
  - Jewelry Designs, 1974 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0027)
  - Kirk Annual Reports, 1974-1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0028)
  - Kirk-Directory of Kirk Employees, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0029)
  - Kirk- Earnings Report, 1978 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0030)
  - Kirk -Flatware - Size of Line, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0031)
  - Kirk - Golden Winslow, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0032)
  - Kirk- House of Kirk (16th century picture), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0033)
  - Kirk -History of Kirk Stieff Co., 1982 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0034)
  - Kirk -History of Kirk Stieff Co.(second copy), 1982 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0035)
  - Kirk International 8/1/1973, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0036)
  - Kirk -Marketing Programs, 1975 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0037)
  - Kirk -Marketing Programs, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0038)
  - Kirk Miscellaneous, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0039)
  - Kirk Pewter, 1973 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0040)
  - Kirk Price Lists- Old, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0041)
  - Kirk Promotions, 1975-1979 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0042)
  - Kirk Sales Conference, 1975 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0043)
  - Kirk Stieff Craftsman Update, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0044)
  - Kirk Stieff Employee Handbook (navy blue folder), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0045)
  - Kirk Stieff Product Develoment, 1983 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0046)
  - Kirk Sterling, Pewter & Silverplate (Blue Notebook), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0047)
  - Kirk Territory Sales, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0048)
  - Kirk Territory Sales, 1977-1978 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0049)
  - Kirk Territory Sales, 1978-1979 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0050)
  - Kirk Marketing Programs, 1975 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0051)
  - Kirk Marketing Programs (Kirk Semi-Annual Promotion Summary), 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0052)
  - Kirk-Stieff Co. & 25th Street Co., 1979 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0053)
  - Lance Corp., 1974 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0054)
  - Lunt Data, 1982 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0055)
  - McGraw Box Co., undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0056)
  - Miscellaneous (includes Court case/Findings), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0057)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0058)
  - Napier Company (misc.), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0059)
  - Napier Giftware Market Study, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0060)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1979-1992 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0061)
  - Oneida, Lunt, Gorham & Yorktowne Pewter, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 1, Folder 2017.7.0062)
  - Packaging, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0063)
  - Pageant of Roses Sterling Flatware & Sales Projections/Weddings, 1962 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0064)
  - Pat Barber - Nadal Line of fine Spanish porcelains, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0065)
  - Patterns and Directory of Flatware, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0066)
  - Pewter Flatware Price Competition, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0067)
  - Pewter Holloware Promotion (Total Year), 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0068)
  - Pewter Holloware Review, 1978 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0069)
  - Pewter Tea set, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0070)
  - Photographs, 1929-1960 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0071)
  - Pictures, 1950-1970s (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0072)
  - Product Development & Review Committee, 1975-1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0073)
  - Promotion - Last Quarter, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0074)
  - R. Wallace & Sons Mfg. Co. Correspondance regarding Stockholders, 1956 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0075)
  - R. Wallace & Sons Mfg. Co. Shareholders' Protective Committee Letters, 1956 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0076)
  - R. Wallace & Sons Mfg. Co. Shareholders' Protective Committee Letters, 1958-1959 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0077)
  - R. Wallace Catalog, 1835 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0078)
  - Reed and Barton Acquires Assets of Sheffield Silver Co. of New York City, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0079)
  - Repricing, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0080)
  - Robert Johnston - Sterling Expert, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0081)
  - Sales Conference, 1975 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0082)
  - Sales Conference, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0083)
  - Sales Conference, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0084)
  - Sales Conference, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0085)
  - Sales Conference (black folder), 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0086)
  - Sales Conference Spring, 1978 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0087)
  - Sales Meeting (black folder)-, 1978 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0088)
  - Sales Meeting, 1972 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0089)
  - Sales Meeting, 1975 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0090)
  - Sales Meeting (Wm. Regan's Presentation) lime green folder, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0091)
  - Sales Meeting (Wm. Regan's Presentation) lime green folder, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0092)
  - Sales Meeting Talks, 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0093)
  - Samuel Kirk & Son, Inc. - Cost Sheets, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0094)
  - Samuel Kirk, nineteenth century silversmith, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0095)
  - Silver made in Europe and Mexico, 1961 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0096)
  - Silver Company Gives First Plate to White House, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0097)
  - Silver Flatware Test, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0098)
  - Silver Work in Argentina, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0099)
  - Silver - Queen of Metals, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0100)
  - Sterling Flatware Breakdown, 1938-1939 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0101)
  - Sterling flatware pricing, 1977 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0102)
  - Sterling Holloware (Sterling Flatware 1934), 1939 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0103)
  - Sterling Holloware -Spring Promotion, 1975 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0104)
  - Sterling Says It All (Your Sterling Silver Pattern Selector), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0105)
  - Sterling Silver Audit 1975 - Fourth Quarter Ending (black notebook), 1976 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0106)
  - Sterling Silver Total Sales by Principal Cities (black notebook), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0107)
  - Story of Silver (Typed book compiled for Wallace Silversmiths), 1963 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0108)
  - Study of Metal Tableware Industry by Timothy Jones, 1981 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0109)
  - Talks on Silver by William F. Regan (red notebook), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0110)
  - Talks on Sterling & Pewter 1976 (William Regan ), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0111)
  - TED, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0112)
  - Timely topics - Pamphlet - Publication - Hamilton Watch Co. 1966, 75th Anniv. Issue Dec. 1967 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0113)
  - Towle, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0114)
  - Tuttle Fine Sterling - Green Notebook -, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0115)
  - Voos Tools, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0116)
  - Wallace & Hamilton Data, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0117)
  - Wallace (shipments & sales), 1973 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0118)
  - Wallace 8x10 Glossy Pictures, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0119)
  - Wallace Catalog Prices, 1881-1899 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0120)
  - Wallace Interim Stock Report, 1957-1958 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0121)
  - Wallace News, 1943-1946 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0122)
  - Wallace News, 1950-1957 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0123)
  - Wallace Personnel and Salesmen, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0124)
  - Wallace Plant - new, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0125)
  - Wallace Price Lists, 1973 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0126)
  - Wallace Silver Holloware(Blue Notebook), 1973 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0127)
  - Wallace Silversmiths -Outline and History of Silver, Design, and Manufacturing Principles & Practices ( Notebook), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0128)
  - Wallace Silversmiths -Outline and History of Silver, Design, and Manufacturing Principles & Practices ( Notebook) copy 2, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0129)
  - Wallace Silversmiths Manufacturing Memoranda (Blue Notebook), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0130)
  - Wallace Sterling mixed order (small black notebook), 1953-1960 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0131)
  - Westmoreland Sterling, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0132)
  - W. J. Regan Miscellaneous (Red Notebook), undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0133)
  - William Regan's Slides on Silver, undated (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0134)
  - Hoffman Goblet, 1945 (Box Cabinet 6- Drawer 2, Folder 2017.7.0135)